How's lunch?
Good.
More importantly, how you're keeping your well.
Yeah, it's good stuff.
Just that curiosity, what was for lunch?
When people feed back, one of the things they always feed back on.
I was just looking at a feedback for a conference.
That was that for you.
That conference is shall remain nameless.
And one of the things people critique was the lunch was terrible.
I'm hoping your lunch was really good.
And if nothing else, it buys me a couple of seconds to kind of feel what's
happening in this space.
So feel very fortunate to be here, really fortunate to be here.
And we find myself in a very interesting time at the moment,
really interesting time.
And it's amazing kind of where we have found ourselves.
Just even in the last five years, let alone the last decade.
But I think one of the things that's always interesting to think
about is kind of what my dad refers to as the mundanity of life.
So the simple things that make people happy.
And what the greatest sites are around that.
And for me, personally speaking, the greatest site that I see is a kid in a park.
Completely free, emancipated, unencumbered.
They're just free.
They're just playing free.
And as you get older, you lose that for a lot of reasons.
You know, life wears on you.
You get these residual scars.
You know, you don't kind of fly across the monkey bars as you might do.
You're a bit more attentive about what you may do because you don't hurt yourself.
And when I kind of think of that freedom and that belief to hit free as a child,
I kind of think what arrests that as you become older.
And then if you kind of narrow that even more as kind of a guest
researchers do, you kind of think about spaces.
And I guess in this context we're talking about a classroom space.
And the freedom and the artistry that, you know, a pedagode may have
in using all of their arsenal and just being that kid in a park,
to being free, just being able to teach unencumbered,
emancipated, free, that freedom.
And you kind of think what restricts that.
When you watch that, well, when you see it, it's poetry emotion.
You look at it and you think, oh my God, you have taken the most difficult concept
and you've made it so easy to understand.
And I always had this idea around when I used to observe certain people,
you know, in, you watch lots of keynotes.
You obviously, you attend lots of lectures, all of these kind of things.
And it wasn't a person, yes, obviously mastery of theory
and all of these things is really, really important.
But the person that I gravitated towards the most,
I suppose you had the mastery of all of that,
but could take a simple message to convey in a very simple way.
And it was really funny during the pandemic.
I think his name was Professor Vantam.
Can't remember his name.
Vantam, but he had, he kind of garnered a reputation
for basically taking really complex messages
and making them really simple for the general public to understand.
So I think famously he said, look, we're free now down
and, you know, we're going to work our way back into this,
you know, but it's going to be tight in terms of talking about COVID.
And you're kind of thinking that someone at the highest level
of kind of trying to explain these things,
but it was very simple analogy that most people could kind of grasp
and they could, you know, that praxis element.
And I guess the difficulty of being in these spaces now,
besides performance indicators,
are that there are pressures on people which mean they can't hit free.
They can't be that kid in the park in the classroom space.
And when you think about it and you see it, it's restricting.
You know, and I had a friend who wants to explain to me,
you know, Jason, being a lecturer in higher education now
is like kind of, it's like trying to do something
with two hands tied behind your back.
You can't be as you were.
There's too many things you have to think about.
You have to think about students as faction.
You have to think about if you're kind of thinking broadly
in terms of the intersection.
You know, my friend who said this to me just to be clear
was a woman of color.
And she made it very clear to me that there are certain things
that I have to think about in the classroom space.
I can't just go in there and just kind of shoot
from the hip so to speak, pedagogically speaking.
And said all of these factors become really decisive anchors
and levers in terms of the decision-making I make,
which means that I'm not free when I'm doing it.
And sometimes I feel like I'm being quite robotic.
I'm doing everything they need.
But am I giving them what they want?
Because when it comes to it, I'm going to say
if there's any complaints about me that, well,
I've done what I was supposed to do.
And I guess is that whole idea of what do people need
and what do people want?
And look, with these things,
there's all the privilege to touch to it.
You know, who is allowed to belong in a classroom space?
Who is allowed to be expressive?
Who is allowed to exercise freedom of speech?
And I say that because I think we're living in a time
where people abuse that most precious of privileges,
freedom of speech, people abuse it.
And in the classroom space,
if we kind of believe what we hear,
that's where we're kind of brainwashing all of these people
who are going to the labor market
and then speak this utter woke nonsense.
I don't think like that, but this I'm paranoid.
And it's interesting.
It's just interesting to kind of see where we are.
And I think all of it comes back to this central seed of
values and belief systems,
in any kind of teacher training program.
I think the first thing you're taught is
what are your values and belief systems as a potential teacher?
And for whatever reason, and it happens to all of us,
it can be quite remarkable how far you can be made to stray away
from those values and belief systems.
One, through compliance,
two, because the landscape of higher education
is very, very different in terms of what students expect
and the consumerist nature of it kind of takes away
the soul of it.
But again, it goes back to that kid in the park.
When you meet an adult who is silly,
the first thing I don't think is why you're silly.
The first thing I think is,
how have you managed to keep that childlike hubris?
How have you managed to not?
How has life managed not to get to you for you to keep that?
And then when I think of someone I look at in a classroom space
and you see the energy, you see the verb,
you see all of it together, you think,
how do people manage to do that?
But then from one classroom to next, increasingly,
you're seeing that people are struggling more and more
to keep that.
And I guess the question is why?
Why?
And it kind of refers me back to one of the important
and the most important things that I think we all have
as individuals, which I think is agency.
You know, there is a privilege attached to agency of course,
but it's that idea of this is my playground.
This is my domain.
Now, what you can't be afraid to do is to hit for the lines.
So at the moment, I guess as a sector,
you know, we've all been corralled into hitting inside the lines.
Right, none of us are hitting big anymore.
I'm generalizing for the purpose of this conversation,
but we're not hitting big anymore.
We're playing it safe.
You know, will we get a ball backing court?
Yes.
Will the ball come back to us?
But it gets to a stage where you think, okay,
do I want to hit for the lines?
Do I want to be the person to take the point?
Or do I want to be dictated to in terms of what I can do?
Now, there's a lot of idealism attached to what I'm saying,
but it is situated in this idea of hope and the idea
that actually our pedagogies and the way we operate in these spaces
are something much more powerful than just being at the front
and doing something.
You know, these things shape people's lives.
They shape people's understanding of the world that they eventually
will be contributing to.
And that charge is so important.
It's so important that we have to kind of protect that
as much as possible.
Now, how do we protect that in the higher education sector
that we find ourselves in now?
I think the idea of vulnerability in those spaces
becomes really, really important.
And part of it is an acceptance that actually
knowledge construction is a two-way streak.
So, for example, the premise that I always work from
is that yes, I am being self-deprecating,
but it is true.
99% of the time.
The people that I've talked throughout my career
are a lot more intelligent than I am.
I know a lot about a very small area.
And the great thing about being a student,
as we've all been, most of us,
is that you learn a lot, you know, along this wide spectrum
and then if you go into academia, you get to more narrow
and narrow and narrow and narrow.
But the essence of having that broad structure
is really, really important.
And I guess for people who are,
when you're teaching people,
one of the things you're thinking is right,
is there an opportunity for,
I always have this idea that if someone walks in
or looks peaks through the window,
I don't want them to be able to know
who the person conducting the learning is
because the idea is to facilitate that space.
But now someone might look at that and kind of think,
well, that shows a lack of control
or, you know, exercising pedagogy in the sense
that actually I'm here to teach and you learn.
But for me, it's that idea of how do we take something,
you know, as transient as pedagogy
and make it as just normal as anything,
a conversation between two people,
a conversation between a group of people,
recognizing, recognizing that when you go into any space,
you work from the presumption, the generous presumption
that people know.
So one of the things that I deliberately don't do
is that I don't use slides.
One, because I don't know who I'm talking to,
that's the first thing.
Two, because I don't work on the presumption
that people don't know.
Now, why does that become hugely important?
Because if we look across the intersection,
those types of deficit ways of thinking
often apply to minoritized groups.
So the presumption is you don't know
or you are not as competent or you're not as able.
And we could do that across the spectrum
because that is true.
But the most important thing is working with that generous assumption
that people know.
And then it's feeling your way through it.
But to do it, you have to trust yourself.
Now, I'm not saying I'm great.
I'm not, if anything, as my friends always say,
Jason is the most underwhelming person you'll ever meet,
which is true in part.
But it's also mainly for the fact that I watch home in a way
and I'm very proud of that.
So that's part of their us and out.
But one of the things that is really, really important
is that idea of how do we trust ourself in these spaces?
How do we trust ourself in these spaces
when you have all of these things coming in?
The societal context, the political context,
the institutional context, the policing of particular individuals
in the institutional context, the policing of how we engage
in these types of pedagogies?
How do we actually create this collective
that we're looking for?
And I think a huge part of it is the human element.
I think the human element has been extracted
from these pedagogical spaces.
And by the way, the reasons are absolutely legitimate.
You know, universities have become factories
and I think we all can accept that and we understand that.
But there is that regard action there
that we can push back against some of these things.
And the reason why I say that is because it goes back
to that values and belief system.
What is the reason I actually became an educator
in the first place?
What is the reason?
Sometimes it's not the most complex things.
It's the most simple things.
Why did I become an educator in the first place?
A few months ago, I was saying to myself,
I was teaching a lesson
and everyone left the group
and a student came to me.
And I'd say so much wrong.
And I said to the student,
I don't know how to explain it.
I don't really think it's appropriate for me
to tell you what I'm thinking.
And I'd go on and I said to them,
that was the brown stuff.
And they were like, what?
I was like, that was crap.
And I was like, well, I think it was crap.
I was like, I said,
do you want to hit free?
You want to be free.
Like, I'm succumbing to something that I'm not.
I'm doing the things that I'm supposed to be doing.
But that's not where you're living.
Being in this space, being an educator,
being in that space, it's like living.
I said, it's another life I'd love to be a rock star.
That will never happen.
But this is the closest thing you get to being one.
And I said, you've got to bring people with you.
And that was just a lesson in how not to do it.
And I was like, well, you were teaching research methods
and I was like, yeah, I know.
But yeah, I know.
I know.
It says more about me.
But I was kind of saying to them,
there's ways to make this,
and by the way, I was teaching something that should really
be of massive interest to me.
And it was around ethnographies.
But for whatever reason, though, just wasn't there.
It wasn't there.
And it wasn't like it was just one bad show.
It was several bad shows.
And I was thinking, on the stub hub,
these people need their money back.
And I asked myself, why?
Why?
And what were the people to guide me in steering me
under the right direction?
I had an innocuous conversation with my adult daughter.
I was not particularly interested.
But my 11-year-old was.
And I'd picked him up from football.
And I said to him, he asked me, he said, as I always was.
I said, did you express yourself today now?
I said, yes, I did.
He said, did you express yourself?
I said, not so much, not so much my dog wasn't.
I was a bit rubbish today, to be honest.
And he said, why was you rubbish?
And I said, I taught some lessons and just flat.
Not very good, blah, blah, blah.
And he said, do you know what?
Daddy, you always talk about hitting free.
Did you hit free?
Did you express yourself?
I said, no, not really.
He said, what are your afraid of?
You always say to me what you're afraid of.
And I said, I don't like it in trouble.
And he was like, you get in trouble at your age.
I was like, no, I'm the very scarediest person
of getting in trouble.
I said, you think when I tell you off, it's bad.
I said, listen, you've got a whole lifetime to get used
to being told by someone.
And he said, and he just said something really simple.
Why do you worry about getting told off?
I said, because it's consequences.
And he said, yeah, but you always wanted to be an educator
from what you said to me.
And you're doing something you love.
So why you think, why are you scared of getting told off?
And I thought, and then the next conversation was
that what we had for dinner.
And I was like McDonald's.
Because a good one was cooked.
But then I thought to myself, yeah, why am I scared?
Why am I scared?
And you kind of think, why don't people teach in that free way
that kind of emancipatory free, unencumbered way?
And the big part of it is because like a kid in the park,
today I know what you become, you're scared of getting in trouble.
If you do something wrong, a student can write to the module leader,
then you get that kind of interesting email which says,
dear Jason, I hope you're well.
Well, it doesn't ever say it's just dear Jason, comma.
If possible, just like to have a quick word with you.
And you know where it's going.
You know where it's going.
And it's always that a couple of students
and a couple of students is like one.
And you kind of think to yourself like, and those emails,
like what they become as a reference point,
they become a reference point for basically making yourself
really, really small in these spaces
and just kind of doing what you need to do.
But it's that whole thing of actually what would make me big
in these spaces.
And the big part of it is to almost let go of that fear of failure.
If I get it wrong, you know, I'd rather, you know,
I'd rather get it wrong trying to be as expansive,
hitting and doing it the right way than getting it wrong.
And someone might say, well, that's a costly endeavor, Jason.
That's really costly endeavor because we're dealing with students
and if you get it wrong, it's consequential.
But it's not because I do genuinely believe
that students pick up on these things.
And I also think there is, as custodians of the academy,
there is an expectation that what we provide them with
goes beyond the classroom space.
I do think there is a responsibility there
to contribute towards producing good citizens
and systems that can contribute to a multi-cultural,
multi-ethnic, multi-diverse society in a myriad of ways.
And just beyond theories, they actually have to be able
to know how to apply those theories in a real-life context.
And so a huge part of this is being able to use your full repertoire
of instruments.
You know, how do we do it?
How do we use all of those things within our toolkit?
And part of it is being that kid in the park,
not being afraid to make mistakes,
not having this expectation that actually, you know,
if I make a mistake it's seen as weakness,
or it's seen as maybe I'm not knowledgeable.
The other side of that is that there are,
particularly ethnic minorities on the sharper end of this,
that deficit approach positions them as not being as competent
or not being as able.
And again, it's why I work with the premise that you walk
into a space and you just work with the generous assumption
that people know, you know, it's the greatest respect
I think you can pay people.
And I guess for people across the intersection,
in some way, shape or form, people have felt
and experienced that deficit way of thinking towards them.
But the thing that I would ask you to step into
and to embrace myself included is to try and hit free,
to try and hit free and to think about how we can work
in kind of collaborative circumstances,
how we can work in terms of these kind of collaborative pedagogies.
You know, team teaching is not novel,
but I think the ways we do it,
that peer engagement, that collegiality, in these spaces,
it has become lost.
And one of the reasons it's become lost actually
is not necessary to do with pedagogy anymore.
It's to do with something that is rewarded really handsomely
in academia and that's kind of individualism.
There's a vanity and an individualism that is rewarding
in academia and it actually isolates us.
It completely disrupts our charge and it does the absolute opposite
of engaging as a collective.
And in such divisive times within a societal
political and economical context,
the need for us to be collective
has never been more important,
particularly in these collegiate pedagogical spaces.
And as my mom always says,
the word to wise is enough,
so I want to bore you to tears after lunch,
but just I would urge you to kind of think about
that if you think of what is the greatest vision or image
you can think of in terms of when you see someone completely happy.
For me, like I said, it's a kid in the park.
And if I think back to being a kid myself,
I think I was at my happiest when I was in the park
staring into the sun and when you stare into the sun,
it's like coderizing, it's sort of red.
You're like, this is bliss.
And you think to yourself, how do I get that feeling back?
And it's about really how we are in these spaces.
And embracing it.
And I guess that idea of failure.
You know, I had to chew at college.
You always used to say, like, you should respect failure,
but you should never be paralyzed by it.
So don't be afraid to fail in these pedagogical spaces.
Don't be afraid to try new things.
Don't be afraid to work collaboratively
and work towards
this side of collective empowerment.
Empowering people in these educational spaces right now.
Well, it's always been since time and more in,
but even more importantly now, I think that is the greatest gift
that one can give a person.
I was going to make a reference to building the car,
but I don't want to speak too much.
So thank you.
I really, really appreciate your time.
I'm always mindful of talking at people.
I'd rather talk with people.
I appreciate all of you.
And if nothing else, you've heard the rumblings of a madman
from South London.
So hello, goodbye.
And I appreciate it.
Thank you.
Cheers.
Thank you so much.
And that does leave us with plenty of time for that space
for, again, connection, engagement, discussion together.
So I have the mic, and I'll bring it around.
Would anybody like to?
Yes, I can see.
Hands up there.
Thank you, Kerry.
I didn't expect to be first.
Thank you, Jason.
That was really, very empowering.
I came here today to be a bit well-nourished,
and I feel a bit more nourished.
So thank you very much for that.
A big question to you.
You're speaking very broadly and bravely
about our needs to really think about the profession
and what we've come here to do.
How do leaders manage that against the complexities
that you've spoken about?
What do we now need to do in a practical way
to help our colleagues to hit free?
That's great.
Thank you so much.
I appreciate it.
It's difficult.
I think, from afar, I'll speak for myself.
Sometimes I've been privately very critical of leaders.
I feel like they have a huge amount of agency and power,
and they don't always utilize that in the best ways.
I think it was until I became a senior leader in higher education
in a previous role, but I realised it's kind of easy to take
pop shots when you don't have to do it.
I think for leaders, one thing I do think is universal
or should be more universal is leading bravely.
I think leaders struggle to make the brave choices
and part of the brave choice is around hitting free.
It is around giving people as much freedom as possible
to be able to exercise their art, because pedagogy
in its raw recents is the art of teaching.
That art has been sanitized a lot,
and not always, but a significant amount of time
that is because of the actions that senior leaders impose
on their staff.
The one thing I would always probably encourage senior leaders
is to try and remember is that you're working with these individuals.
They're not beholden to anyone.
You're working with these individuals, and it's really important
that you see them, and you recognise their capabilities
and provide them with all the apparatus available
to execute their charge to the best of their abilities.
I think senior leaders are taking that away a bit more and more
and more by distributing power ironically in the wrong places.
And I think that's important.
I think it's important for senior leaders to obviously hold power
and they do effectively distribute it,
but it's about who has access to that power,
and it's about really where possible,
eliminating hierarchy as much as possible.
I don't believe in hierarchy, and I never have,
so I've never been deferential to that.
There's a need for hierarchy.
I understand why it has to be there,
but I also think leaders, senior leaders,
recognise in their significant pressures that they're under
do also need to tend to the people that they are working with
because that's hugely important.
And while we're on that subject actually,
I think the mental health of staff is a really, really significant thing.
I don't think we've ever been in a time where
I'm in the process of collecting the data for this,
and I don't ever make references to my own research,
but the data that I'm collecting at the moment is to find out
how many staff across the sector over the last three years
have been on sick leave, and I haven't got the data in front of me
but I'm in the process of getting that data from HESSA
and other agencies, but it's significant.
And I think that the mechanisms in place support staff
while being a mental health have completely forgotten
these kind of factories now.
And I think senior leaders have a duty of care to their staff
and I think by recognising that duty of care,
they will actually have better outcomes, better pedagogical outcomes
for those staff, and most importantly, the students.
You're welcome. Thank you.
Thank you, Jason.
Like my colleague, I also found your talk very nurturing and comforting.
And I really appreciated how you, I feel like you've modeled
on the ability you've talked about making mistakes
you've spoken with outside. I really appreciate seeing that model.
So thank you. And I just wanted to ask you,
how do you manage it on a personal level
because you feel like you're bringing
and you're encouraging us to bring our whole cells
and there is a cost involved in that?
Well, that's a great question.
Shall I answer honestly?
I feel I'm scared.
And the reason I'm scared is not because I think students are dangerous.
I just think we're living in dangerous times.
And I think there are so many things that arrest
educators to be able to do what they really want to do in spaces.
Regardless of where I sit on the political spectrum,
I just think that everybody is finding it hard for lots of different reasons.
I think the reasons I find it hard
and I think many people find it hard is because I genuinely think
that you are one error away from losing your job.
And I don't think that's a particularly nice space to be in.
And I don't think it encourages people to be free in that space.
In a way that is not harmful to other people.
And if you spend too much time kind of thinking about something like that,
you just don't flow. You don't think everything becomes very structured,
very regimented, and very prescriptive by its very nature.
And I guess I just worry about that.
I worry about that a lot because you're worried about making mistakes.
And when I first started teaching, when I started as a peer teacher,
I never had that. Like, I never had that.
I was just, I was free in my head.
I knew exactly what I needed to do.
I knew exactly how I wanted to do it.
And then you kind of, and even the beginning of my career in higher education.
But then weirdly, the more agency you got as you kind of were doing,
you were going up the ladder.
You feel that that's the more kind of jeopardy you feel.
You feel like if I say something wrong here, it's hugely consequential.
And given the nature of the work that many others do across the intersection,
including myself, it's a really precarious time to be in.
And I've known many people who have said something in class,
and have been given a verbal warning,
or a secondary warning for a gross misconduct, and have found themselves out of work.
And I'm not exaggerating when I say that.
And by all accounts, what they're saying is, you know,
they're relating to either aspect of their research,
or they're talking about a phenomenon in terms of, you know,
intersectional inequality, whether it be racism, sexism, homophobia,
ableism, you know, religious inequality, all those types of things.
Yeah, I try to rest that.
And I try and go for it.
I try and go for it as much as possible.
I think the thing that's different now is that everything...
I never really said too many wrong things before,
but I think the difference is over the last three years,
everything you say is of consequence.
I always knew that, but I never really felt it
where as now I'm like, you say one thing you're going to nup in the telegraph from page.
And that's my fun.
I think having to think in that way,
but I don't think that's exclusive to me.
I think that's everybody in this room in some way, shape or form.
And it's difficult.
It's difficult.
But, you know, when a kid goes into a park and they fall off like
the kind of climbing bars or a climbing frame,
you know, it doesn't perturb them from going back on it.
And I love that.
I love that.
You know, as an adult, if we fell off something now,
the likelihood is like, I'm not doing that again,
because I don't want to get hurt.
But with the kid, they just...
They're just like, okay, this hurt, but I'm going to do it again.
And I guess what I'm saying is I don't want us to...
I want us to try and find that in pedagogical spaces.
They still didn't go so well,
but what are the learnings I can take from it
and how can I do that differently?
And I think that difference can happen
when you're working with people.
Is that how I have safety in numbers?
The collective empowerment and empowering
and enriching each other, I think is so, so important
because in this sector, you know,
there are people who behave in ways that I think are really
abhorrent and unacceptable,
but ultimately we're all we have in this sector.
And I think it's really incumbent on us to look after one another
and to enrich one another and to really pour into each other.
And I think that's how you do it.
You're welcome.
I'm sorry.
I'll pass it over.
Here.
Thank you.
Hi, Jason.
My name's Amanda.
I was really struck by your comment about failing and failing
safely.
And I think one of the things that I would be keen to hear from you is
how do we create spaces where students can fail safely.
I think given the pressures, particularly in Russell Group
institutions, in post-as-indrome, value for money with
degrees, there's a lot of pressure on us and our students to
just be the best all the time.
And actually sometimes failing in a safe environment is just as
valuable.
So I guess your thoughts on how do we encourage that and how do
we bring that out of our students?
I think that's a great question.
And in a word, I think probably humility and vulnerability.
I know there's a foreign concept in academia, but I think
humility is hugely important in those spaces and vulnerability.
I often tell students not to placate them, but to tell them as
the truth that you guys are much better than I'll ever be,
which is the truth.
There's no shame in conceding that.
I've obviously done okay in the area that I specialised in,
but there's no shame for me.
I'm speaking for myself in terms of conceitations.
You know, more than me.
So part of this is that we learn from one another.
We learn from one another.
It's not about one upmanship or trying to show off or
you know, certain swinging exercises.
It's about learning and that can happen between all of us.
And I think having the humility to exercise that humility
in the first place, it gives the students, in many respects,
a licence to feel vulnerable to be able to fail.
Also given them kind of context, which is that,
particularly I guess, maybe in rust group context, this isn't
everything.
This isn't everything.
And that is something that I tell students very often.
Like, the things that I think students should focus on,
the first and most important thing is being a good human being.
And unfortunately, I don't always think that that lesson
is modelled very well in academia because it's very nature
around being individualistic, the vanity aspect,
people treat people by and large pretty badly.
For not really any good reason that I could fathom
or construct.
And I think it's important to model to students how important
it is to treat one another with respect, with dignity,
create spaces belonging.
And part of that is modelling that.
And we can do that by one, being humble in these spaces
and recognising that we don't know everything.
Two, eliminating hierarchy as much as it's possible to do so.
And look, I totally understand that there's privilege
to attach that because there are certain people who can't actually
they have to exert a form of not hierarchy authority
because they are positioned as deficit in the first place.
But I think where possible, I think one of the things
that can disarm people, I think most people is kindness.
And I do think the thing that disarms just about everybody
in my opinion, which is more to do my upbringing,
is humility.
And if you bring kind of vulnerability into that space,
I think it's a really powerful elixir.
And I think if students see that and it's like,
look, it's good to fail.
It's good to fail.
The reason why it's good to fail is because you will learn from it.
You will learn nothing from being successful all the time.
It's good to learn that.
And if we can model that as pedagogues in these spaces,
I think it's a nonbelievable job in very, very trying times
because it's about creating obviously really good students
but the most important thing, the central, most important thing
is about creating or contributing towards creating good human beings.
And I think my whole thing was I'll never be the best academic in the world
when I'm close to it.
But what I can aspire to be is the nicest academic in the world
or the kindness that that's a great aspiration to have, not that I am.
But it's a good aspiration to have.
And I tell students that because very often they'll ask me,
what did you do to get to where you got to?
And I always explained to them, it's not about getting there.
It's the way you did it. Did you bring people with you?
Did you treat people with respect where you recognized the people that came before you?
That created the pathway for you to be able to traverse the path around.
It's these types of things that matter.
And the rest of it kind of follows in suit.
It's what I do, and it's sort of touched with it's sort of work for me.
So you seem like you've got an amazing handle on it, but hopefully that might help.
You're welcome.
Hi, really great touch speech. I absolutely loved it.
One question I did have was you talked around kind of enabling,
not assuming people have the knowledge that they would have the knowledge.
One question I had was, what if by doing that you're ostracizing students?
So you've pushed, you've assumed.
Can I just, can you hear me?
Yeah, I can, sorry.
What do you do?
Oh, is it for the, okay.
Well, I'll yell and try and not to break the mic at the same time.
So what do you do when you're by assuming people know what they're doing,
or that they're the smartest people in the room, that you inadvertently ostracize them,
because they don't know, and then you've gone, but you do know,
and then they feel like they can't show that vulnerability,
because you've made that assumption.
That's a great question. I really appreciate that.
So this gives me a chance to explain that actually.
So, I think the thing is you create a space for learning.
So part of me making the assumption, not that I necessarily say it,
I make the assumption, which is a positive assumption,
for people to be able to feel those, though they can engage and ask questions in that space.
If I give the impression that people don't know,
my feeling has always been that you can suppress what people know,
and actually position yourself as knowing more.
On top of that, I guess the feeling, or the philosophy,
comes from my own lived experience,
and that of many people of color in particular,
which is that when you walk into a space,
people just never think you are who you are.
And because I know what that feels like,
I know what that feels like, and I know which I never ever be on.
I always work with the most, you know, there's a generosity
in working with the perception or the belief or the philosophy
that somebody may know, in creating and facilitating a space,
where they can exhibit that knowledge in a way that is
collective, collegiate, and kind of embraces everyone.
You know, as opposed to being the person in the room
that you just make an assumption on.
And so I've often tried to work with that premise in my mind,
because, like I said, I've been the person that people do that to,
and that's not unique to me.
There are many, you know, up until maybe three years ago,
you'd go to places and, you know, people would be like,
I'm looking for Jason.
I'm Jason.
You know, I think it's an old, it's a tried and tested one,
but it's true.
I've lost count at a number.
I'm using people of colour for this particular example,
but I've lost count at a number of people who say to me,
so someone comes in the room, and they say,
sorry, you decline.
I'm just about to, I'm just, I've got a lecture,
and they'll say, no, no, I'm X, Y, and Z.
And, by the way, there's absolutely, you know,
the contribution that domestic staff make to these institutions
to argue more important than anything we do.
Much more important in my eyes, especially coming from a family
of people who have cleaned myself and cleared it.
But what is interesting is how people position these things
as a hierarchy in their mind, and they see that as a deficit
approach to work to, you know.
So, if someone says, you know, oh, I thought you were a student,
you know, some days you're like, I'll take that,
and some days you're like, I'm looking about 50 today,
so I don't accept that.
And by the way, that positioning is always interesting
because you kind of know when that's happening.
So, I think that generosity is hugely important,
and I think, like I said, for a lot of people who've been
on the end across the intersection,
might I add, of that kind of deficit way of thinking,
that I feel like the greatest gift I could give to someone
is to presume that you are whole and that you know.
And then give you the opportunity to engage in that learning
because in that sense, you're starting from here,
and you can kind of, you can choose where you put yourself
on that scale.
But if I start you from here, you know, your opportunity
to show me any different would be based purely
on my conscious or unconscious biases.
So, that's what I try and do.
That's not to say it's a hard science, and it works all the time.
It's kind of a work in progress.
It has been since I was 25, some don't have 16 years.
So, yeah, you're always trying new and different things,
but I think it's a huge kind of respect that I'm showing
to people when I presume that they know,
because I mean it from the bottom of my heart,
and I mean it with the best of intent,
because I think it's unkind when you look at someone
and make a judgment and you're like, you just don't know.
You don't know to look at somebody, you know,
and I know which judgment I would prefer
if I had to make one.
Jason.
Yeah, Jason.
Thank you.
I love your radical humility and pedagogy of love
and all those kind of things.
I mean, you mentioned intelligence,
and you said there's lots of people
who are intelligent than you.
I kind of feel like that as well,
and as far as the question for me is this issue
of imposter syndrome.
And I know that it can affect anybody and everybody,
but in a place like what if I think it probably,
you know, ironically I think it affects a lot of students
because I think that in a place that's possibly the best
and the cleverest,
do we need to abolish the concept of intelligence?
Is there a violent concept that's implicated in
the reality,
especially disabled people,
or Black people of women?
A few years ago,
we had a component,
what if it was called intelligence squared after you remember that?
What if you can double your intelligence or something?
Right.
So it's just a kind of thought about imposter syndrome
and what reproduces that in these kind of institutions.
One is so great.
LAUGHTER
So...
One,
Gernam, thank you so much.
I can't,
without embarrassing professor Gernam seeing a current
emphasize how influential his work has been
for a lot of people from Black and Brown.
I think minority backgrounds who have tried to do work
in this space,
and it's crazy because they kind of say
you should never meet your heroes and people you look up to.
But, you know, when I first met Gernam
pretty 12, 10 years ago,
the same person I met is,
and I hoped he would be the same person he is now.
And when you see more examples where that doesn't happen,
you truly realize how special that is.
So firstly, thank you for that.
I really appreciate you.
And just about everyone who's come up with me
does as well.
In terms of the imposter syndrome,
I think it's...
It's always a really interesting thing.
My whole thing about the intelligence thing
is that I do think it's a colonial hangover.
I do think it's a colonial concept I agree with you.
I guess it depends what people add currency to.
So...
I don't, I'm not intelligent,
but what I do have is wisdom.
And I also have the wisdom to know
that, and this is just my personal belief,
I don't think,
and I hope I don't sound like a narcissist.
I don't suffer from imposter syndrome.
And the reason why I don't is because I believe
where I ended up is where I'm supposed to be.
And I also was taught from a very young age,
knowing that I didn't have any academic acumen whatsoever,
that skill can be measured,
but will is indomitable.
So I knew that will couldn't...
It's not something you can measure.
It's just about giving it everything you've got
and admittedly along the way I got very, very lucky.
And I think the thing that I've always worked towards
is to ensure that luck doesn't come into it.
In other words, you know,
I want more people to be where they're supposed to be.
It's not about kind of these sliding doors moments
and stuff like that.
And yes, I worked as hard as I could,
but there's people who've worked just as hard,
if not harder, who have not had yield,
who have not been yielded or gifted the same rewards.
So you recognize very quickly that, yes, in some ways,
I have closed the gap by working as hard as I can.
So I don't feel imposter syndrome in the same way,
but I also recognize that the work to be done
is to ensure that actually people feel this sense
of not entitlement, but this sense of,
I do deserve to be here.
And a huge part of that comes from diversifying the space
and trying even harder to ensure that there are more people
in space as well as one or two,
because that is not collective empowerment.
That is individualistic.
Thank you.